hello everyone my name is greg and i def
staff welcome everyone to episode 12 of
the tactics game in unity refactoring
mouse controls
today we will refactor our mouse control
to remove the repeated code about mouse
control which will allow us to create
nice interface between player and
gameplay
create a new object called game manager
set position to zero
we want to decouple the mouse input from
systems we already have implemented like
move character character
attack etc etc instead we will create
script called mouse input which will
manage all of the mouse input it will
centralize all the
interaction with mouse
in one place and everyone who needs a
mouse input data will reference the
script
inside we need to make a field for the
camera we will be using so in case you
will be having multiple cameras on the
scene you will be able to specify which
camera to use for your control scheme
set the camera in the editor
while we here let's turn off all the
components on the camera
we need to add target grid and terrain
layer mask
so we will be able to interact with the
grid and specify a physical layer where
this grid is placed
set them in the editor
now in the update shoot the ray out of
the mouse position on the screen from
the main camera
then cut the raycast
good so now let's introduce a public
variable called position on grid which
will store the position our mouse is
currently over
we hit the terrain with this raycast
convert the hit point into the grid
position
then compare the hover over position to
the grid position in the update if it's
not equals that means our mouse moved
and change the position and we need to
update position on grid
this episode is brought to you by
generous support of people on patreon
and members on youtube if you want to
join them link to my patreon in the
description and join button available
right now on youtube
with this mouse input script we have
decoupled mouse
and from now on if you need to read
position of the mouse just read it off
the mouse input script
we will migrate the
move character attacking script in the
next episodes when we will start
introducing command patterns
now let's introduce a marker on the map
to make it
more clear where our player is pointing
at with his mouse
and this will allow us to demonstrate
how mouse input works in this episode
create another new script called marker
open the script
and here we need to create a reference
to the transform of our marker object
create a marker object
reference marker object in the marker
script
cache the mouse input so we will be able
to read the mouse input in the marker
create current position variable and
target grid serialized variables
to update marker position only every
time your mouse changes the position on
the grid compare the current position
in case they are not equal it means the
mouse moved on the grid and we need to
update our marker position
by getting the world position on the
node from the target grid
set the target grid and let's test this
it works but our marker is too small and
heats underground
so we need to introduce an elevation
add the elevation to y position
now when our mouse input is not hovering
over the ground we want to hide our
marker
in the mouse input if we hit something
let's set public ballarable called
active to true otherwise in else set it
to false
that means if our raycast doesn't
collide with the ground it means it's
hovering over something else like
outside of the boundaries for example
and we should not try to show the marker
when we are not hitting our terrain
in the marker create a new variable
called active which will store the state
of our marker
is it active on the scene or not in case
our mouse input is not active we want to
disable our marker and if it is active
then we want to enable our marker to
show it to our player
if our marker is inactive we don't need
to update the marker position
so add exit gate here
and make sure you move the active check
above the exit gate
look it works
but occasionally throws an error this is
happening because we are trying to get
the position outside the boundaries
so add an exit gate
based on the check
boundary
good this is it for this episode if you
have any questions or any ideas about
code please leave your comment below if
you're interested in seeing what will
come out of this please subscribe if you
want to support further you can find my
patreon in the description special thank
you to andrew v long and the salt hush
do for their generous support with best
regards see you in the next episode
you